Finding aid for the Collection of Armenian Manuscripts, ca. 1300-1899 LSC.2089
UCLA Library Special Collections
Collection of Armenian Manuscripts
ca. 1300-1899
UCLA Library Special Collections
LSC.2089
91 items
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
PORTIONS OF THIS COLLECTION HAVE BEEN DIGITIZED. See the Existence and Location of Copies note for the link to the digitized materials.
General note
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942327033606533
Scope and Content
Collection consists of Armenian manuscripts from the 14th to 19th centuries, mostly from the Minasian Collection. Many are in contemporary bindings.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digitized materials are available electronically at https://digital.library.ucla.edu/catalog/d2xg9000zz-89112.
Related Material
Minasian Collection of Armenian Material (Collection 1632). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Minasian Collection of Near Eastern Manuscripts (Collection 1147). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Armenia -- Civilization -- Archives.; Armenia -- History -- Archives.
- Collection of Armenian Manuscripts, v.p. (Armenia), 14th-19th centuries; (15 boxes, 88 items)
  Scope and Contents note
  Most of the manuscripts are from the Minasian Collection. Many are in contemporary bindings.
  Preliminary checklist of the manuscripts by Professor Avedis K. Sanjian:
  - 170/466 - Four Gospels, (p.00), A.D. 1300-1307; MS 1.
  - Four Gospels, A.D. 1327; MS 2.
  - Four Gospels, probably 17th Century; MS 3.
    General note
    [shelved in vault]
  - Four Gospels, A.D. 1643; MS 4.
  - Grigor Tat'ewac'i's Book of Questions, A.D. 1637; MS 5.
  - Commentaries on the Four Gospels, A.D. 1648; MS 6.
  - Commentaries on the Song of Songs, after A.D. 1650; MS 7.
  - Miscellany, A.D. 1690-1700; MS 8.
  - Giardino Spirituale, A.D. 1693; MS 9.
  - Book of Sermons, 17th/18th Century; MS 10.
  - Brief Treatise on the Seven Sacraments of the Holy Church by the Vardapet Georg K'oc'ec'i/julayec'i, A.D. 1737; MS 11.
  - Miscellany, A.D. 1742; MS 12.
  - Nerses lambroniac'i's Commentary on the Divine Liturgy, A.D. 1811; MS 13.
  - The Shield of Faith by Mik'ayel C'amc'ian, A.D. 1823; MS 14.
  - John Chrysostom's Commentary on the Book of Isaiah, A.D. 1847; MS 15.
  - Menologium, 17th Century; MS 16.
  - Menologium and Sermonary, 18th Century; MS 17.
  - Menologium, 17th Century; MS 18.
  - Menologium and Sermonary, 18th Century; MS 19.
  - Ritual Book, 15th/16th Century; MS 20.
  - Ritual Book, A.D. 1513; MS 21.
  - Ritual Books, A.D. 1580 and 1667; MS 22.
  - Fragments from Three Ritual Books, 16th/17th Century; MS 23.
  - Ritual Book, A.D. 1693; MS 24.
  - Ritual Book, 17th/18th Century; MS 25.
  - Ritual Book, 17th/18th Century; MS 26.
  - Ritual Book, A.D. 1807; MS 27.
  - Ritual Book, A.D. 1814; MS 28.
  - Ritual Book and Other Texts, A.D. 1817; MS 29.
  - Ritual Book, A.D. 1825; MS 30.
  - Ritual Book, A.D. 1830; MS 31.
  - Calendar of Feasts, 14th/15th Century; MS 32.
  - Liturgical Texts, A.D. 1460-61; MS 33.
  - Hymnal (Fragments), 16th Century; MS 34.
  - Psalter, 15th/16th Century; MS 35.
  - Liturgical Texts (Fragments), 15th/16th Century; MS 36.
  - Fragments from a Psalter, 16th Century; MS 37.
  - Hymnal, 16th/17th Century; MS 38.
  - Psalter, 15th/16th Century; MS 39.
  - Hymnal and Calendar of Feasts, !.D. 1650; MS 40.
  - Breviary, A.D. 1678; MS 41.
  - Liturgical Texts, A.D. 1650; MS 42.
  - Psalter, Early 17th Century; MS 43.
  - Hymnal, 17th Century; MS 44.
  - Calendar of Feasts, 17th Century; MS 45.
  - Breviary, 16th/17th Century; MS 46.
  - Prayer Book, A.D. 1711; MS 47.
  - Grigor Tat'ewac'i's Book of Sermons: Volume I, Jmeran, A.D. 1754-68; MS 48.
  - Grigor Tat'ewac'i's Book of Sermons: Volume II, Amaran, A.D. 1630; MS 49.
  - Book of Sermons, 17th Century; MS 50.
  - Sermons and Other Texts, 17th Century; MS 51.
  - Book of Sermons, A.D. 1710; MS 52.
  - Theological and Other Texts, A.D. 1699-1706; MS 53.
  - Miscellany, A.D. 1563; MS 54.
  - Miscellany, A.D. 1656; MS 55.
  - Miscellany, A.D. 1662; MS 56.
  - Miscellany, 17th Century; MS 57.
  - Miscellany of Theological Works, A.D. 1725; MS 58.
  - Miscellany, 18th Century; MS 59.
  - Miscellany, A.D. 1836; MS 60.
  - Nerses Šnorhali's Works, 16th/17th Century; MS 61.
  - Collection of Canticles, 17th Century; MS 62.
  - Book of Odes, A.D. 1798; MS 63.
  - Minstrel Yart'un Olli's Daftar, Before A.D. 1840; MS 64.
  - Anthology of Poetry, After A.D. 1522; MS 65.
  - Pharmacopoeia, 16th/17th Century; MS 66.
  - Amirdovlat' Amasiac'i's "Useless to the Ignorant" and Other Works, 16th/17th Century; MS 67.
  - Amirdovlat' Amasiac'i's "Useless to the Ignorant", 17th Century; MS 68.
  - Calendrical and Other Texts (Fragments), 18th Century; MS 69.
  - Pharmacopoeia, 18th Century; MS 70.
  - European Pharmacopoeia, Early 17th Century; MS 71.
  - Armenian Canon-Book, A.D. 1618; MS 72.
  - Geomancy and Other Texts, A.D. 1625; MS 73.
  - A Brief Lexicon of the Books of the Bible and Other Texts, A.D. 1696; MS 74.
  - Simeon julayec'i's Summa of Logic, 17th/18th Century; MS 75.
  - Mxit'ar Sebastac'i's Concise Book of Rhetoric, A.D. 1758; MS 76.
  - Readings from the Book of Daniel, 18th Century; MS 77.
  - Interpretation of Dreams and Treatise on Planets, A.D. 1769-80; MS 78.
  - Catholicos Aristakes II's Encyclical Letter, A.D. 1475; MS 79.
  - Brief Canticles, 19th Century; MS 80.
  - Anthology of Popular Songs, A.D. 1906 or Earlier; MS 81.
  - Fragments of a Menologium, 17th Century; MS 82.
  - Menologium (Fragments), A.D. 1882; MS 83.
  - Collection of Poems, 1896-1927; MS 84.
  - Menologium (Fragments), A.D. 1882; MS 85.
  - Commentary on the Gospel of Matthew (Fragments), 19th Century; MS 86.
  - Readings from the Book of Daniel, 19th Century; MS 87.
  - Fragments from Gospels, 14th/15th Century; MS 88.
  - Menologium (Fragments), 17th Century; MS 89.
  - Encyclical Letter by Catholicos Abraham Kretac'i, A.D. 1736; MS 90.
  - The Story of the Seven Sages (in Armeno-Turkish), 18th Century; MS 91.
  - 170/766 - Gospel of the Myrruhbearer